<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter from a gentleman in the country to his friend in London occasioned by a prophesie that was lately found in the place of retirement of Father Lewis at Comb, in Hereford-Shire ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1393A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27370586</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 27370586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter from a gentleman in the country to his friend in London occasioned by a prophesie that was lately found in the place of retirement of Father Lewis at Comb, in Hereford-Shire ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption Title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Satire on St. David Lewis, who was executed during the Popish Plot, 1678-9.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lewis, David, --  Saint, 1617-1679 --  Humor.</term>
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110086:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
            <head>A LETTER From a Gentleman in the COUNTRY, To his Friend in LONDON.</head>
            <head type="sub">Occaſioned by a PROPHESIE, That was lately found in the place of Retirement of Father <hi>Lewis,</hi> at <hi>Comb</hi> in <hi>Hereford-Shire;</hi> he being the Party that undertook, for the value of thirty pounds, to pray the Soul of a certain Maids Father out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, (the which) hath lately been made mention in a Pamphlet.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe News which daily occurs to us in the Country, doth give me frequent Opportunities of preſenting my Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to you; I am very glad, that you are ſo kind to me, as to do me the Honour, to employ me to give you an Account of our quotidian Tranſactions; But on the other ſide, I am ſorry that you will find no better entertainment, when you come into the Country, than now you are like to have. For our French-Wines were long ſince, quite ſpent, and our better Wine, our <hi>Redstreak</hi>-Sider is almoſt drank up, for Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Lewis</hi> and his Accomplices were moſt inſatiable Drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and would never be at quiet, till they had gotten our Liquors from us; and though that Holy-Father was ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious, as to demand but thirty (out of five and thirty) pounds of the Maid, to pray her Fathers Soul out of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory (which if well done, might in Reaſon, deſerve a hundred) yet he was ſo Deviliſh unkind to us, as to threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en us, that we ſhould drink no more Sider after his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe; The verity of which, you ſoon may find, if you pleaſe to Read the Coppy of a Propheſie which he left behind him; It is as followeth.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110086:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
               <head>The Propheſie.</head>
               <p>BEfore the Glorious <hi>Luminary</hi> of the Day ſhall this year Enter into the ninth of the Caeleſtial Houſes, there ſhall happen ſtrange Revolutions, to the great Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of many. Deſarts ſhall become populous, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Populous places ſhall be almoſt deſolate. Divers Fertile places ſhall grow Barren, and ſome Mines ſhall be exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. There ſhall be Apparitions of Men in Bloudy-colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Robes, ſhaking of Chains, to the great Terrour ofl the Beholders. In many places ſhall be heard wonderful and unintelligable Voices, to almoſt the general Conſternation of all thoſe that hear them; and by means thereof, ſome ſhall be ſo enchanted, that for ſome conſiderable time, they ſhall not be able to ſtir from the Magick-Ground. Divers grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sighs and Complaints ſhall be uttered, which ſhall even penetrate the Hearts of thoſe who hear them, whilſt others ſhall rejoyce to ſee Bloody Slaughters and great Fires, which ſhall then be in many places. Many things which for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Ages have been kept in profound Secreſie, ſhall be then brought to light, and made to appear as clear as the Noon-day. Vineyards ſhall lye waſte, Pomaries ſhall be rifled, and divers Structures ſhall be Demoliſhed; inſomuch, that Corn ſhall hereafter grow in the places where they once ſtood.</p>
               <p>This Propheſie was ſtrangely and miraculouſly found out, for our Gentleman of the two legged Tree, having a Months mind to try whether a Prieſts Garments would become him, going one Morning to try how Father <hi>Lewis</hi> his Doublet would ſit him, by chance eſpied a Gentleman, which much accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies the Black-Guard, creeping out from between the Lining and the Cloath, which he intends to ſend to <hi>Rome,</hi> there to be kept alive, for Zealots in future Ages to go in Pilgrimage to; and that he might be ſo much further meritorious, as to oblige other Romiſh Churches (beſides St. <hi>Peters</hi>) with ſome of thoſe Relicts, he falls to Ripping up the Doublet, not daring to truſt a Taylor with a matter of ſo great importance; leſt by him
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:110086:2"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
he ſhould be cheated of ſome of thoſe ſix-footed Animals, and ſo his intended pious Deſignes ſhould be performed by another. He had no ſooner thruſt in his Knife, with an intent to Rip up the ſtitches, but on a ſudden out leaps the Propheſie, and away vaniſhes the Doublet, ſo that he thinks his deſires are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, for he doth really believe, that every Church in the Popes Dominion is furniſhed with one of the beforementioned conſecrated Gentlemen. This is all the News I can at preſent inform you of; but when there happens more, I will give you notice of it by the next, in the mean time if any thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens at London worthy your pains of writing, pray Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it to your Friend and Servant,</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation_of_prophecy">
            <head>The <hi>PROPHESIE</hi> Explain'd.</head>
            <p>
               <label>Propheſie.</label> BEfore the Glorious Luminary of the Day ſhall this year enter into the ninth of the Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Explanation.</label> 
               <hi>Sagittarius</hi> is the ninth Houſe, into which that Glorious Luminary the Sun enters upon the tenth of <hi>November,</hi> being near the middle of <hi>Michaelmas</hi> Terme.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Deſarts ſhall become populous, and many populous places ſhall be almoſt deſolate.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> Thoſe People who in the long Vacation went into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and deſerted <hi>London,</hi> will towards the Term come up again to Town, and leave the Country almoſt Empty.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Divers Fertile places ſhall grow barren, and ſome Mines ſhall be exhauſted.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> Some Clients who came up with full Purſes, will then go down with ſcarce a Croſs in their Pockets: and thoſe who were trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with more vexatious Suits of Law, will likewiſe be forced to ezp<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd greater and more conſiderable ſums of money than others need to do.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> There ſhall be Apparitions of Men in Bloudy-colour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Robes, ſhaking of Chains to the great Terror of many of the Beholderss</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:110086:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
               <label>Exp.</label> Before the Term the Seſſions will be held in the <hi>Old Baly,</hi> where the Lord Mayor, the Sherifs, and ſome of the Aldermen will fit in their cSarlet Robes, with Golden Chains about their Necks, and thoſe Priſoners who are Conſcious of their Guilt, will tremble, when they are brought to be tried at the Barr.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> In many places ſhall be heard wonderful and unintel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligable Voices, to almoſt the general Conſternation of thoſe who hear them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> In the ſeveral Courts of Judicature, the hard terms of the Law will be made uſe of, which many perſons cannot underſtand.</p>
            <p>Pro. And by means thereof, ſome ſhall be ſo enchanted that they ſhall not for ſome conſiderable time be able to ſtir from the Magick-ground.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> Some againſt whom Verdicts have paſſed, will be Arreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and impriſoned, till they have paid the ſums of mony, in which they were Caſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Divers grievous Sighs and Complaints ſhall be uttered, which ſhall even penetrate the Hearts of thoſe that hear them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The poor Priſoners in ſeveral places are apt to Sigh, and make ſad Complaints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Whil'ſt others ſhall Rejoyce to ſee Bloudy Slaughters and great Fires which ſhall be in many places.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Butcher muſt kill their Beaſts, and the Poulterers their Foul, and the Cooks muſt have good Fires or elſe they cannot dreſs them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Many thing which for ſeveral Ages have been kept in profound Secreſie, ſhall be then brought to light, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon ſome Trials, Antient Records muſt be produced.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Vineyards ſhall lie waſte.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> Becauſe the Grapes will be all gathered befors that time.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Pomaries ſhall be Rifled.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> The Orchards will have no Fruit left in them.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Pro.</label> Divers Structures ſhall be demoliſhed, inſomuch that Corn ſhall hereafter grow in the places where they once ſtood.</p>
            <p>
               <label>Exp.</label> 
               <hi>Sturbridg.</hi> Fair is kept in a Corn field, and the Builders of the Booths are obliged to pull them down before the end of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that the Field may be Ploughed. <hi>And now I bid the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der farwel, hoping he will be ſatisfied with this Explanation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
